<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-05-24T18:38:54+08:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Logos</title><subtitle>Science Literacy in the Misinformation Age</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Constellations &amp;amp; Conspiracy Theories</title><link href="/constellations-and-conspiracy-theories" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Constellations &amp; Conspiracy Theories" /><published>2020-05-14T18:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2020-05-14T18:00:00+08:00</updated><id>/constellations-and-conspiracy-theories</id><content type="html" xml:base="/constellations-and-conspiracy-theories">&lt;p&gt;Detection of the Higgs-Boson, gravitational waves, the creation of quantum computers, just to name a few.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s very easy for most people to dismiss them as being “dumb,” or “ill-informed,” but the reality is that conspiracy theorists are only human, like you and me, with the same capabilities of thought as everyone else.  Be careful of thinking they are different and you are the smart one, because it’s the same type of hubris they themselves have for you and your thoughts.  If you look a little bit deeper, you will find we have more similarities than differences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all fall victim to our own minds sometimes.  Recognizing our own brain’s weaknesses is the best way to defend ourself from that.  Everyone believes in one at some point in their lives. You, me, everyone… even the world’s preeminent scientists. (Will get to that later)  Chances are you still currently believe at least one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s no way we can eliminate them entirely, our minds are built to build beliefs, it’s just our nature.  But with a little forethought and knowledge, we can at least make sure the bad ones go extinct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-do-we-believe-them&quot;&gt;Why Do We Believe Them?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are several factors:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-confidence--unsupervision&quot;&gt;1. Confidence + Unsupervision&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;./assets/images/ct/dunning-kruger.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Dunning-Kruger&quot; style=&quot;width: 300px&quot; class=&quot;align-left&quot; /&gt;
Also known as &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dunning%E2%80%93Kruger_effect&quot;&gt;Dunning-Kreuger Effect&lt;/a&gt;, operating together with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Four_stages_of_competence&quot;&gt;hierarchy of competence&lt;/a&gt;.  These are famous biases where people with low ability tend to &lt;em&gt;overestimate&lt;/em&gt; their ability, because of their inability to recognize their own lack of ability.  &lt;em&gt;Unskilled and Unaware of It&lt;/em&gt;, was the title of Kreuger &amp;amp; Dunning’s famous paper.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;./assets/images/ct/hierarchy-of-competence.png&quot; alt=&quot;Hierarchy of Competence&quot; style=&quot;background-color: #ccc; margin-top: 1.5em;&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then there is the Hierarchy of Competence, which goes for all skills.  Most people are unconscious of their incompetence, and this applies to almost every human skill, which includes reading about news and current events.  People assume because they read every day, they can see the world, but there is no correcting mechanism to supervise if you are right or wrong. This plus confidence will lead people to assume they are right about every conclusion they come to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-sometimes-they-are-true&quot;&gt;2. Sometimes They Are True&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;./assets/images/ct/snowden-film.jpg#thumbnail&quot; alt=&quot;Snowden&quot; class=&quot;align-left&quot; /&gt;There are many examples of this, just from my home country of America:  Watergate, Project Sunshine, MK-Ultra, and NSA mass surveillance.  The fact that some are true may lead others to a very rational conclusion that others can true as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-unfalsifiable&quot;&gt;3. Unfalsifiable&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Einstein is famously quoted as saying:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;No amount of experimentation can ever prove me right; a single experiment can prove me wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;%20https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Falsifiability&quot;&gt;Faisifiability&lt;/a&gt; is a core scientific principle that states, science only needs one good (&lt;em&gt;repeatable&lt;/em&gt;) experiment in order to disprove an entire scientific theory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem with most conspiracy theories is that many of them are unfalsifiable, with no way to disprove them.  But this isn’t the case with all of them.  Many have been and can be easily falsified by science, such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flat_Earth&quot;&gt;Flat Earth Theory&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vaccines_and_autism&quot;&gt;Vaccines Cause Autism&lt;/a&gt;.  These easily falsifiable theories will hold weight from a segment of the population, due to a lack of understanding of &lt;em&gt;confirmation bias&lt;/em&gt;.  But, falsifying a fact and falsifying a belief are two separate things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;4-confirmation-bias--the-youtube-algorithm&quot;&gt;4. Confirmation Bias &amp;amp; the YouTube Algorithm&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All humans have a tendency to search for and interpret information that confirms their existing beliefs. Once you believe something, it becomes part of your personality, and difficult to dislodge.   This is feeded into by the YouTube Algorithm.  Designed to keep you on the platform for a long time, it  will feed you more information you are likely to click on, further solidifying your beliefs.
	This deserves an entire article of it’s own…  it’s currently one of the biggest problems facing America…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;./assets/images/ct/ctchickens.png&quot; alt=&quot;Conspiracy Theory Chickens&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;three-scientific-explanations&quot;&gt;Three Scientific Explanations&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-evolutionary-theory&quot;&gt;1. Evolutionary Theory&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As early humans, our lives were often violent and dangerous.  The entertainment we enjoy today, such as&lt;em&gt; horror movies&lt;/em&gt;, are a direct result of dangers we used to individually face, which is why we are always attracted to them, to try and imagine ourselves in those situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Horror movies use the same tricks that early humans face.  Our observations vs. our reality.  Most times, our observations and reality line up.  But other times, not so, and we call this &lt;em&gt;error&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;error&lt;/em&gt; comes in two forms, scientists call them:  &lt;strong&gt;Type I&lt;/strong&gt;  and &lt;strong&gt;Type II&lt;/strong&gt;.
Imagine we ourselves are in a horror movie.  &lt;strong&gt;Type II Error&lt;/strong&gt; occurs when, for example, we are in a dark room, and look into the mirror.  We expect to see a ghost.  Oooooooo!  So we look, and OMG!  We see.. ourselves.  No ghost.  Well that’s embarassing, but everything’s fine.
&lt;strong&gt;Type I Error&lt;/strong&gt; is when we think, hey there’s no ghost.  So whatever.  We look in the mirror, and BAM!  The girl from The Ring comes out and kills us.  We’re dead.  Oh crap.
Type I Errors are called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jump_scare&quot;&gt;jump scares&lt;/a&gt; in the film industry.  People think of it as just a cheap trick, but the evolutionary equivalent of jump scares have real, serious consequences, such as being eaten by a crocodile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As humans, we are constantly on the lookout to avoid a Type I Error.  &lt;em&gt;Better safe than sorry&lt;/em&gt;.   It’s better to be mentally prepared for a threat that may not exist, rather than be unprepared for one that does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-pareidolia&quot;&gt;2. Pareidolia&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pareidolia is the &lt;em&gt;tendency of perceiving stimulus, of a pattern or object, as something known to the observer.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;./assets/images/ct/orion-constellation.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Orion&quot; class=&quot;align-right&quot; /&gt;
From the Greek word &lt;em&gt;para&lt;/em&gt; (“alongside”), and &lt;em&gt;eidolon&lt;/em&gt; (“image, shape”).  Everytime you see an elephant in the clouds, or a man’s face on the moon, that’s your pareidolia speaking. All humans have this, and it’s not confined to humans, even computers being trained in pattern recognition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a cognitive bias that all humans are susceptible to.  The tendency to find patterns in the chaos, even if those patterns don’t exist. when Jesus appears on a piece of toast, it’s a holy sign. When a face appears on the Martian surface, it’s the aliens.  But what is the sign when you show them the map of Italy, and you see a boot?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-probability&quot;&gt;3. Probability&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Probability is the scientific way of dealing with uncertainties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a famous 2013 paper, &lt;em&gt;“Measuring Belief in Conspiracy Theories”&lt;/em&gt; a physicist tried to calculate the likelihood of conspiracy theories based on the &lt;em&gt;total number of people required to keep it secret&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which led to the creation of the a &lt;em&gt;Generic Conspiracist Beliefs&lt;/em&gt; scale.  His findings?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Moon Landing: 411,000 people ending in 3.68 years&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Climate Change: 405,000 people ending in 3.70 years&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vaccination: minimum 22,000 people (without drug companies) ending between 3.15~34.78 years&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cure for Cancer: 714,000 people  ending in 3.17 years&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flat Earth wasn’t studied, but just by using a thought experiment, you can tell it’s probably the least likely.  You would need the cooperation of all major governments, airlines, pilots, Armed Forces, Aerospace Companies, NASA, SpaceX, and not to mention the entire scientific community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Judging the likelihood is similar to what we should be doing as humans, but many of us reduce these beliefs to absolute truth or falsehood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is called the &lt;strong&gt;Bias of Absolutes&lt;/strong&gt;.   If someone else has coined this already (which is entirely a likely possibility), I will correct this in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We tend to think in terms of absolute  thinking, but nothing at all is 100% absolute. Even the laws of physics can be up-ended in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should be noted that probability can work &lt;em&gt;to the advantage of&lt;/em&gt; some conspiracy theories.  In 2003, Nick Bostrom, a famous Oxford Philosopher, successfully convinced the entire scientific community, just by using Bayesian Probability and some key assumptions, that we are all likely to be living in an artificial simulation.  This is the famous &lt;em&gt;simulation hypothesis&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;is-so-and-so-conspiracy-theory-true&quot;&gt;Is &lt;em&gt;so and so&lt;/em&gt; conspiracy theory true?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like all things, it depends on the factors. Just remember the &lt;em&gt;Bias of Absolutes&lt;/em&gt;. All theories are never 100% certain, just varying degrees of likelihood. Evidence &amp;gt; anecdotal. Science &amp;gt; your YouTube video. As long as you are aware of your own cognitive biases, it can be fun to entertain the possibilities. The danger is when we take them too seriously at the expense of proven science, such as in the case of Anti-Vaxxers, or the drinking of Bleach during the COVID-19 pandemic.  The wrong information provided to vulnerable people can lead to serious harm, even death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, for most, entertaining conspiracy theories is enjoyable in the same way people like to look at optical illusions.  To close, here are some personal favorites:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Olsen Twins are just one person moving very quickly back and forth
&lt;img src=&quot;./assets/images/ct/olsentwins.png&quot; alt=&quot;Olsen Twins&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Dogs don’t like fetching the ball, but they think we really like throwing it so they keep bringing it back.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Disney made the movie Frozen so when you search for &lt;em&gt;Disney Frozen&lt;/em&gt; you don’t read about a cryogenically frozen Disney&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rocks are soft and squishy, but they get nervous and tense up when we touch them
&lt;img src=&quot;./assets/images/ct/squishyrock.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Rocks are Actually Squishy&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Dean Koontz’s books are written by the golden retriever, and the man is an actor paid by the publishing company, because no one would take a dog writer seriously
&lt;img src=&quot;./assets/images/ct/deankoontz.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Dean Koontz&quot; class=&quot;align-center&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further Reading:
&lt;a href=&quot;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/pdf/10.1111/pops.12568&quot;&gt;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/pdf/10.1111/pops.12568&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencealert.com/equation-shows-that-most-big-conspiracies-would-have-been-revealed-by-now&quot;&gt;https://www.sciencealert.com/equation-shows-that-most-big-conspiracies-would-have-been-revealed-by-now&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0151003&quot;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0151003&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Reza Maakheru</name></author><category term="conspiracy-theories" /><summary type="html">The scientific breakthroughs of the 21st century have been amazing milestones for us as a human race. But segments of the population has fallen victim to some very serious.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Irrationality</title><link href="/irrationality" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Irrationality" /><published>2020-05-09T18:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2020-05-09T18:00:00+08:00</updated><id>/irrationality</id><content type="html" xml:base="/irrationality">&lt;p&gt;We begin with a tragic tale, the story of Hippasus.  The story is well known among the mathematics circles.  Hippasus lived in the 5th century BCE who belonged to a religious sect called the &lt;em&gt;Pythagoreans&lt;/em&gt;, who believed that rational numbers are the heart of the universe.  &lt;em&gt;All is number&lt;/em&gt;, was their motto.  Numbers were at the heart of the divine &lt;em&gt;rational&lt;/em&gt; truth, and Pythagoreans believed they were sacred, &lt;em&gt;rational&lt;/em&gt; things, that held together the cosmos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then came Hippasus, a follower and practitioner of this religion.  He was able to solve the mystery of the diagonal of the square.  If you take a square, each with sides 1, the diagonal will be \(\sqrt{2}\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note, \(\sqrt{2}\) is the first irrational number in existence to be proved, and the pythagoreans, while based on a mathematical religion, is still a religion, with belief systems.  The discovery and existence of an irrational number was considered a form of heresy and a threat to the core of the Pythagoreans, who’s power and influence stemmed from their belief that rational numbers are sacred.  Instead of being rewarded for his discovery, he was murdered.. thrown into the sea to drown by his sect-mates.  Like white blood cells attacking an infection before it spreads and destroys the host.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This serves as a cautionary tale for anyone who is interested in the study of rationality, as well as science.  The world has many of these dark twins… a light and a darkness.  Rational and irrational numbers are not an either-or type of thing.  Anyone interested in its mathematics needs to work with both in a way that is complimentary… The light and darkness together, because one cannot exist without the other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, the best way to study science, you must acknowledge its dark sides, and go to places that even science does not care to look. In pursuit for the never-ending quest for truth, scientists often turn a blind eye to threats to its existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Humans have been the ones to create science, but if we are not careful, we’ll be the ones to destroy it as well.  History is filled with examples of this: the burning of the library at Alexandria, the ending of the Islamic scientific Golden Age, the 800 years of what we call the Dark Ages… Science has encountered significant setbacks and destruction through its history…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is hubris to think that we are immune from the sins of the past, for we are all humans, no different from our ancestors, complete with all same emotions, cognitive bias, and belief systems. We are on track for these traits to become the defining characteristics of humans in the 21st century.  As much as we are fearful of future tech, the reality is that technology only tends to map onto existing characteristics of who we are as humanity.  So if you break down many of the root causes of extinction level doomsday scenarios, they almost always stem from the fallibility of humankind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disclaimer &amp;amp; Footnotes: I first heard of this story after reading Irrationality: The Dark Side of Reason, by Justin E.H. Smith.  It’s a solid read that explains how our pursuit of rationality often unconvers its opposite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should be noted the actual details from story of Hippasus are subject of historical debate.  This is legend, and, like other legends, begins with some basis in truth, but becomes distorted over each telling of the story, like a game of telephone.  Among contemporary mathematicians it is a well-known tale, the origins of which can be traced back to the Pythagoreans themselves.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Reza Maakheru</name></author><category term="irrationality" /><category term="getting-started" /><category term="philosophy" /><category term="science" /><summary type="html">Irrationality is a word we often associate as having some real negative connotations. How do we get rid of it? Is that even possible?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Problems of Modern Philosophy</title><link href="/problems-of-modern-philosophy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Problems of Modern Philosophy" /><published>2020-05-06T04:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2020-05-06T04:00:00+08:00</updated><id>/problems-of-modern-philosophy</id><content type="html" xml:base="/problems-of-modern-philosophy">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Quantum physics, expanding universe, each of which falls so far out of philosophy that the whole community of philosophers were rendered essentially obsolete.Philosophy has parted ways from the frontier of the physical sciences, when there was a day they were one and the same.  - Neil Degrasse Tyson&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you go to any school’s website they have a section “Why Study Philosophy?”  They make arguments how studying philosophy has real practical benefits, such as helping you become a better thinker, to analyze and solve problems logically, and to write and speak clearly.  There are also arguments that philosophy has made advancements and contributed immensely to society.  But to be honest, these same can be said of just about any type of formal study.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As per my last post, philosophy was never intended to be just “asking a bunch of questions &lt;em&gt;repeat to infinity&lt;/em&gt;”, like today.  The &lt;em&gt;answers&lt;/em&gt; are&lt;em&gt; just as important&lt;/em&gt; as the questions.  Philosophy was, at the time, grounded in practical reality, with real-world scientific and military applications.  Knowledge learned from its techniques have enhanced the capabilities of both entire societies and great leaders, such as Alexander the Great and Marcus Aurelius.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s true that even today, the U.S. Military does use a version of philosophy to help in training for its leaders and officers, but they are careful stay away from the title of  &lt;em&gt;philosophy&lt;/em&gt;,  because the meaning of that word today.  Instead they draw from anthropology and evasion of biases in order to shape the minds to become more&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Philosophy and science were not enemies, they have historically been one and the same. Anything science reveals should be something that philosophy should embrace as another victory for truth and the unraveling of the universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But modern philosophy has gone so far from its ancient roots that it is, unfortunately, unrecognizable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;case-1--confirmation-bias&quot;&gt;Case 1:  Confirmation Bias&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a strange trend and you may have witnessed this yourself: in general, the only people to advocate a case that philosophy is relevant are students and learners of philosophy themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In that sense, their belief is a type of &lt;em&gt;confirmation bias&lt;/em&gt;, similar to that of a religion.  Any religion will attempt to claim its beliefs and studies are relevant to the modern age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general, if you need to read an article on “Why Philosophy is Relevant” or “The Benefits of Studying Philosophy,” the articles will have the same amount of bias as a Watchtower Magazine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;case-2-science-is-a-self-correcting-process&quot;&gt;Case 2: Science is a Self Correcting Process&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What refutes science is &lt;em&gt;better science&lt;/em&gt;.
What does not refute science is feelings, beliefs, religions, or your opinions after watching a Youtube video.
Science rarely needs to defend itself.  Virtually no one will challenge its power unless it steps over into the realm of another belief system.  Its benefits to society speak for itself, in the words of Richard Dawkins, “it just works.”
You can think of many powerful modern scientists who add immense value to society.  Stephen Hawking, Albert Einstein, Bill Nye, Carl Sagan, Neil Degrasse Tyson.  Philosophers are a little bit more difficult to name, and certainly not elevated to the level of pop culture. Nick Bostrom([^1](#): Nick Bostrom:  a philosopher who embraces science, and who’s simulation argument has successfully convinced the majority of scientific thinkers, using Bayesian Probability, we are likely to be living in a simulation.) is the closest we have to one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;case-3-philosophy-should-be-self-correcting-but-its-not&quot;&gt;Case 3: Philosophy &lt;em&gt;Should&lt;/em&gt; be Self-Correcting (but it’s not)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modern philosophy tends to go far up into the clouds… it tackles some serious questions about life, the nature of things, and consciousness.  But but never arrives anywhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point, philosophers need to accept that questions are only better when there are practical, “reachable” answers.    When is it enough?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been many cases in history where people have believed something, only to be proven true, or be proven false.  Freud was once considered the authority of psychology, but his theories are considered obsolete today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Philosophy has no such self-correcting mechanism. We should be able to disregard mediocre philosophy the same way we don’t read  the majority of books at the bookstore, or the majority of scholarly papers in academia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are people who continue to study outdated philosophical ideas, and just believe them to be important questions. They ask all kinds of questions, but fail to ask the most relevant question of all: &lt;em&gt;is this important?&lt;/em&gt;  But no, that’s off limits. No one wants to get kicked out of the classroom.  &lt;em&gt;Because I told you so,&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;that’s the way it is,&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;I did it this way, so you should too.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Modern Philosophy has become a bureaucracy.&lt;/strong&gt;  And when senior leaders of a bureaucracy are unwilling to change and adapt, the whole structure stalls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be fair, this is not 100% the fault of philosophy, it’s a general issue that stretches into &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; undergraduate academia.  Adaptive change has been slow and extremely iterative, widely dependent on each individual department. But this is opening up a can of worms that deserves another article in itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;case-4-bad-writing&quot;&gt;Case 4: Bad Writing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, let’s be honest, no one wants to read bad writing, unless they’re making fun of it.  Modern philosophical writing has this bad habit to splatter words on a page and call it philosophy the same way Jackson Pollack splatters paint on a canvas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the general tendency is to blame the user.  &lt;em&gt;You just don’t know enough about it,&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;our thoughts are too complicated for normal people to understand.&lt;/em&gt; And because people on the outside are not experts, this belief usually goes unchallenged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If everyone accepts it as a normal thing, nothing changes.  When you live inside a bubble, you can’t see the mistakes you make in relation to the world outside.  You will likely annoy everyone you try to interact with, and the writing becomes discarded into irrelevancy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;case-5-falsifiability&quot;&gt;Case 5: Falsifiability&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Reproducability&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;falsifiability&lt;/em&gt; are two central principles of science.  This grounds their work into reality and makes sure that science is always working on something that is practical.
&lt;em&gt;Falsifiability&lt;/em&gt; is one of the most important.  Anyone can come up with a crazy conspiracy theory that is unfalsifiable.
Einstein is once quoted as saying “a million experiments can prove me right, but all you need is one experiment to prove me wrong.”  This is what gives some theories power and others not, the fact that you can support or disprove them, and all you need is the correct amount of evidence.
Faisifiability is a core principle of the sciences, the fact that all you need is one solid case to disprove something.
Contemporary philosophy just doesn’t hold this principle … theories continue to circle around questions that don’t have practical answers.  In this sense, they hold just as much weight as unproven conspiracy theories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;but-why&quot;&gt;But Why?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer is the same as any belief system or religion: survival.  In order to maintain their relevance and job security, each generation of philosophers at university needs to maintain the appearance they are doing something important and necessary to society.  It’s a passing of the torch.  Philosophy is no longer a search for truth, it’s a belief system, fighting for survival, morphed into something unrecognizable from its original roots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order for modern philosophy to survive, it needs to evolve.. to find a way to fuse itself back in with science….&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are so many, countless, real-world applications philosophy can teach, of which I have learned firsthand as part of the military.  Critical thinking, wargaming, red-teaming…  Protection against groupthink, scientific literacy… An awareness of cognitive bias and how to combat it.  Sun-Tzu, Clausewitz, Marcus Aurelius…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A re-emphasis on self-improvement, of which philosophy was the creator of, in the form of the stoics.  The current U.S. infestation with fake news and bad science, of which philosophy needs to and must take a commanding role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead what does it focus on?  The nature of consciousness.  How do we know what we know?  If a tree falls in the forest does it make a sound?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I realize I’m making some preposterous arguments, and I show my bias against philosophy itself.  But as a human race, we are facing some real, serious, threats…  end of the world type of scenarios.  Misinformation, fake news, antiscience… all of which are causing immense harm, and setting us back years, decades, perhaps centuries of progress.  &lt;em&gt;Where are the truth-seekers?&lt;/em&gt;  Our world is being taken over by sophists, and modern philosophers are concerned more with themselves. Philosophy not only needs to embrace science, but be its chief defender against threats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, modern philosophers are more concerned with defending themselves from arguments by scientists saying they are not relevant.  This is perceived as an attack, but scientists by nature see observable, objective truths.  If you have to defend yourself from the observations of scientists, you are probably not yourself seeing objectively…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disclaimer:  I will say this, I am lumping all of modern philosophy into a basket of “badness,” but there are always exceptions.  Philosophy is not dead, but the one’s that I respect now are ones who have embraced science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick Bostrom is the clearest example of this, who has put forth convincing arguments that we are probably living in a simulation.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Reza Maakheru</name></author><category term="getting-started" /><category term="philosophy" /><category term="science" /><summary type="html">Scientists like Stephen Hawking and Neil Degrasse Tyson famously dismiss modern philosophy as obsolete. Philosophers are “would-be scientists without a laboratory.”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Protagoras &amp;amp; Logos</title><link href="/protagoras-and-logos" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Protagoras &amp; Logos" /><published>2020-04-27T18:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2020-04-27T18:00:00+08:00</updated><id>/protagoras-and-logos</id><content type="html" xml:base="/protagoras-and-logos">&lt;h2 id=&quot;protagoras--the-sophists&quot;&gt;Protagoras &amp;amp; the Sophists&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 5th century BCE, Greece was populated by &lt;em&gt;sophists&lt;/em&gt;: people  trained in the art of persuasion and influence.  They are often paid large sums of money by politicians and leaders, in order to teach them the ways and methods on how to effectively command and influence others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Protagoras was one of these sophists, the most famous of his time.  His treatise &lt;em&gt;Technique of Eristics&lt;/em&gt;, or “Practice of Wranglings” made analogies to wordplay being a &lt;strong&gt;zero-sum game&lt;/strong&gt;.  Victory is achieved in one of two conditions: you had to either win, or force your opponent to lose. “To make the weak argument the strong.”  Was his motto.  And just like a dirty type of war, rules can sometimes become a secondary objective.  Deception, influence, power, greed… anything and everything can and should be used to win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The sophist is one who gains power or money from an apparent but unreal wisdom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;plato--the-logos&quot;&gt;Plato &amp;amp; the Logos&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plato was one of the first of the &lt;em&gt;truth-seekers&lt;/em&gt;.  He believed in the &lt;strong&gt;logos&lt;/strong&gt;, the existence of one, single, universal, truth of the cosmos.  In modern terms, this idea fused together the arts of science, philosophy, and mathematics all into one simple idea. You can think of it as the ancient equivalent of the modern Physicists’ Grand Quest for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theory_of_everything&quot;&gt;Theory of Everything&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plato lived in a world where he watched these &lt;em&gt;sophists&lt;/em&gt; squabble for scraps of influence, status, and other such insignificant things. It must have felt like watching animals in a zoo.  You can see how this idea gained mass appeal, for some people are just not so interested in fighting. In comparison to this divine truth, this knowledge of the gods, mortal affairs began to look increasingly insignificant. Philosophers began to invoke this &lt;em&gt;logos&lt;/em&gt; the same way that Star Wars uses &lt;em&gt;the force&lt;/em&gt;, because absolute truth was considered knowledge of the gods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And legend says this is when the ancestral line of &lt;em&gt;philosophers&lt;/em&gt; began to diverge from the &lt;em&gt;sophists&lt;/em&gt;.  Like Jedi being ideologically divergent from the Sith.  From Plato’s simple statement came a renaissance of ideas: the Stoics, Mathematics, Epicureans, Pythagoreans, the Gospel of John.  This simple idea broke the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The philosopher is one who seeks wisdom and truth above all things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Logos(Greek) -&amp;gt; Ratio(Latin) -&amp;gt; Reason(English)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most philosophers believe that reason itself was not always locked inside human minds… rather, it permeates and gives shape to the order of the universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When truth is the ultimate goal of a debate, there are no losers.  The truth is a &lt;strong&gt;win-win&lt;/strong&gt; for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Plato’s followers grew, they began to recognize the absurdity of the sophists’ arguments.  &lt;em&gt;Sophisms&lt;/em&gt; they called it, little explosions.  Smoke bombs, distractions, set off to confuse or stun others, in order to advance their own interests. This became what logicians call the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Principle_of_explosion&quot;&gt;Principle of Explosion&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Ex falso sequitur quadlibet&lt;/em&gt;, from false, anything follows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does this sound familiar?  Fake news, misinformation, we are literally drowning in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even in high school debate teams across the U.S., we prize influence and persuasion over the truth. It’s been so entrenched in our culture as to go unchallenged for several decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way to see is to go deeper than the arguments themselves.  How do you uncover the truth?  The question lies inside each person’s heart, that motivation that drives them.  What is it they advocate?  Is it the truth? Or something else…&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Reza Maakheru</name></author><category term="getting-started" /><category term="logos" /><category term="sophists" /><category term="philosophy" /><category term="rationality" /><summary type="html">If Platonic philosophy had a villain, it would be Protagoras, of which Plato himself was influenced as an example of what *not* to follow. Plato is the one who gave rise to the idea of *Logos*, the absolute truth. It’s hard to discuss Logos without first discussing the climate which gave rise to it.</summary></entry></feed>